Finding Aid for Institute for Social Research (University of Michigan) records 1936-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- ISR Administrative Files 1949-2013, 40 linear feet
  - Assistant Directors Topical Files 1949-1989
    The Assistant Director's Topical Files consist of 2 linear feet of material and date from 1949 to 1989. They are primarily the files of James Wessell, although some files of Stanley Seashore are included. These files reflect the responsibilities of the assistant directors who had oversight of ISR policy and personnel. Of note are the Affirmative Action files, the files on the building addition, and tenure. The files of the Center Administrator Group document this group's focus on administrative issues, space needs of the staff, services and facilities, and the recommendations given to the Administrative Committee.
    - Accounting 1967-1969 (Box 21)
    - Affirmative Action 1967-1988, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Anonymity 1962 (Box 21)
    - Assistant Director Job Responsibilities 1959, 1963 (Box 21)
    - Audits 1952-1982, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Black Action Movement 1970 (Box 21)
    - Budget
      - General Funds
        - 1964-1971 (Box 21)
        - 1981-1989, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Building (see also Space)
      - Architectural Plans 1969-1972 (Box 21)
      - Financial Plans 1969-1972 (Box 21)
      - Addition/Alterations Bidding Requirements prepared by Alden B. Dow Associates, Inc. 1974 (Box 21)
      - Floor Plans 1978 (Box 21)
    - Business Office Manuals 1981-1982 (Box 21)
    - Center Administrator's Group (CAG) Agendas Minutes and Notes
      - 1976-1978 (Box 21)
      - 1980-1991, 4 folders (Box 22)
    - Center for the Research Utilization of Scientific Knowledge 1969, 1984-1989 (Box 22)
    - Central Services 1974-1986 (Box 22)
    - Committees
      - Affirmative Action 1974-1980 (Box 22)
      - Communications 1972 (Box 22)
      - Computer/Computing Policy 1970-1978, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Historical 1971-1979 (Box 22)
      - Training 1962 (Box 22)
      - Urban Development 1968-1969 (Box 22)
    - Computers
      - Computer Services Facility Oversight Group 1967-1981 (Box 22)
      - IBM 360/40 1965-1977 (Box 22)
    - Development 1965-1969 (Box 22)
    - Director's Search Committee 1976-1976 (Box 51)
    - Diversity Initiatives 1987/88 (Box 22)
    - Emeritus Status 1981-1989 (Box 22)
    - Field Office 1969-1983 (Box 23)
    - Graduate Students 1970-1980 (Box 23)
    - Growth 1960-1968 (Box 23)
    - Hayes and Associates Professional and Administrative Salary Study 1972-1977 (Box 23)
    - ISR Director Review 1980 (Box 51)
    - ISR, Inc. 1969 (Box 23)
    - ISR/University of Michigan 1949-1965 (Box 23)
    - Library 1969-1971 (Box 23)
    - Overhead 1969 (Box 23)
    - Publications 1954-1984, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Rensis Likert Associates Inc. 1970-1989 (Box 23)
    - Retreat 1988 (Box 23)
    - Social Research Applications 1968 (Box 23)
    - Space 1956-1966 (includes NSF proposal for building) (see also building) (Box 23)
    - Tenure 1961-1968 (Box 23)
    - Vice President for Research 1974-1982 (Box 24)
- Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK) 1962-1985
  The subgroup Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK) dates from 1962 to 1985 and consists of 1.25 linear feet of material. There is good documentation in this series for the formative years of CRUSK, including transcripts for the planning sessions of the University Advisory Committee which met from 1962 to 1963. The Director's correspondence, although not complete, includes notes from Ronald Lippitt and others about the formative ideas of such a center. The reports are especially useful for the first six years of CRUSK, when the center was funded by the W.K. Kellogg Foundation. Documentation of the decision to close CRUSK in 1986 exists in the ISR Director's Topical Files and the ISR Executive Committee minutes.
  - Director's Files
    - Committees
      - Advisory Committee 1965-1966 (Box 24)
      - Structure Committee 1965-1966 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence and Notes 1959-1969, 4 folders (Box 24)
    - Review and Planning 1969-1971, 1985 (Box 24)
  - Reports and Proposal
    - Proposal for the Establishment of CRUSK, January 1964 (Box 24)
    - "CRUSK Status and Planning Report No. 4," 1964 (Box 24)
    - "Leadership, Organizational Effectiveness, and Human Resources," Status and Technical Report 1964 (Box 24)
    - "An Exploratory Study of Knowledge Utilization," 1966 (Box 24)
    - "Knowledge Utilization: An Emerging Discipline and Profession," 1966 1967 (Box 24)
    - W.K. Kellogg Foundation Grant Annual Reports 1967-1972, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - "An Overview of the Center and Its Activities Through Charts and Tables: January 1968 through December, 1968" (Box 24)
    - "A Policy Statement for CRUSK," 1973 (Box 24)
    - "Organizational Development Research Program: Statement of Interests and Qualifications," 1978 (Box 24)
    - Yearbook and Annual Report 1982/83-1983/84 (Box 24)
  - University Advisory Committee
    - Memos and Notes 1963 (Box 25)
    - Planning Session Transcripts and Summaries
      - Seminar on Research Utilization 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Seminar on Research Application 1963 (Box 25)
- Research Center for Group Dynamics (RCGD) 1936-1960
  Research Center for Group Dynamics (RCGD) records date from 1936 to 1960, measure 1.75 linear feet and include primarily the papers of Director Kurt Lewin, including manuscripts and talks. The talks and manuscripts are arranged alphabetically although the titles given are a mix of the name of the talk and the place the talk was given. These documents are especially useful for insight into research Lewin was conducting on issues relating to minorities, especially the Jewish minority, and how he saw his research as contributing to social change in this arena. The correspondence with the Field Foundation is useful for documenting the initial years of RCGD at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology; the UM correspondence documents communication between Dorwin Cartwright and UM before RCGD moved from MIT to UM.
  - Director's Files
    - Budget 1950-1953 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence
      - Field Foundation, Inc. 1943-1948 (Box 25)
      - University of Michigan 1947-1948 (Box 25)
    - Reports and Notes
      - Report on RCGD 1946-1949 (Box 25)
      - The Current Activities and Plans of RCGD 08/15/1947 (Box 25)
      - Report About the RCGD for the Marshall Field Foundation for the First Two Terms of the Research Center (Box 25)
      - Report on the Status of the RCGD 08/13/1946 (Box 25)
      - RCGD at MIT (Sociometry) Undated (Box 25)
      - Notes on 1948 Planning Sessions 1948 (Box 25)
      - Report of RCGD, July 1 to December 31 1949 (Box 25)
      - Reports to Office of Naval Research 1952-1955 (Box 25)
    - Personnel Records 1947-1960, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Talks (Alphabetical)
      - Academy of Science 01/18/1946 (Box 25)
      - Advisory Research Council 01/26/1946 (Box 25)
      - Advisory Board Talk 04/14/1946 (Box 25)
      - American Jewish Congress 05/30/1946 (Box 25)
      - Bureau for Intercultural Education 03/29/1946 (Box 25)
      - Bureau of Youth Education Undated (Box 25)
      - Commission for Community Interrelations and Rogosin Center 09/18/1945 (Box 25)
      - Cincinnati 11/29/1945 (Box 25)
      - Connecticut, "Techniques of Intergroup Relations," 03/27/1946 (Box 25)
      - Council for Civic Unity, Los Angeles, June 1945 (Box 25)
      - Group Loyalty in a Democracy Undated (Box 25)
      - Group Problems and World Reconstruction 11/22/1945 (Box 25)
      - Hillel 05/14/1945 (Box 25)
      - Hillel, Michigan 05/31/1946 (Box 25)
      - History of Commission for Community Interrelations and Priority Problems in Action Research, 1/46 (Box 25)
      - Individual in the Group, A.H. Murray 08/30/1946 (Box 25)
      - Jewish Child Welfare 12/12/1945 (Box 25)
      - Jewish College Students' Attitudes toward Themselves, Hillel September 1946 (Box 25)
      - League 10/22/1945 (Box 25)
      - MIT Faculty Meeting Talk 10/17/1945 (Box 25)
      - Mt. Holyoke 04/13/1946 (Box 25)
      - New York State Dietetic Assoc. 05/14/1946 (Box 25)
      - Newtonville Temple Talk 12/14/1945 (Box 25)
      - NCRAC, Chicago (Box 25)
      - Personality, Harvard (Box 25)
      - Place of the commission on Community Interrelations within the Work of the Jewish Organizations 11/16/1944 (Box 25)
      - Philosophy and Broader Goal of CCI 02/15/1945 (Box 25)
      - Postwar Research 06/16/1943 (Box 25)
      - Psychological Problems in Jewish Education 04/11/1946 (Box 25)
      - Relation of Jews to Jewishness Undated (Box 25)
      - Research in Group Process 05/13/1946 (Box 25)
      - Science, Philosophy and Religion 1945 (Box 25)
      - Social Workers Conference Undated (Box 25)
      - Temple in Brookline, "The Jewish Child in the War World," 01/11/1946 (Box 25)
      - United Settlements Undated (Box 25)
      - Vassar & Bennett Jr. College 11/09/1945 (Box 25)
      - Where do We Go From Here? (Box 25)
      - Yale 12/19/1945 (Box 25)
    - Manuscripts (Alphabetical) (Box 26)
    - Action Research and Minority Problems Undated
      - A Basic College and Field Program in Group Dynamics Undated (Box 26)
      - Behavior and Development as a Function of the Total Situation Undated (Box 26)
      - Cassierer's Philosophy of Science and the Social Sciences Undated (Box 26)
      - Conduct, Knowledge and Acceptance of Values Undated (Box 26)
      - Group Decision and Social Change Undated (Box 26)
      - Measurement of Forces Undated, 3 folders (Box 26)
      - Minority Problems and Science (Box 26)
      - National Occupational Conference, Psychological Problems involved in Success and Failure 1936 (Box 26)
      - Problems of Group Dynamics (Box 26)
      - Problems of Group Dynamics and the Integration of the Social Sciences: II Channels of Group Life, social Planning, and Action Research Undated (Box 26)
      - Project of a Research Institute on Leadership and Group Organization Undated (Box 26)
      - Psychological Conditioning of Children Undated (Box 26)
      - Remarks Concerning Rehabilitation (Box 26)
      - Research for Social Survival Undated (Box 26)
      - Solution of a Chronic conflict in a Factory Undated (Box 26)
      - Material for Papers and Articles and Misc. (Box 26)
- Survey Research Center (SRC) 1946-1980
  The Survey Research Center subgroup comprises almost 26 linear feet of material and includes Committees (5.25 linear feet), Correspondence, (1.75 linear feet) Director's Files (7 linear feet), Policies, Press Releases and Reports (.75) and Project and Proposal Files (12 linear feet).
  - Committees and Other Groups 1946-1980
    The minutes and agendas of several committees, including Council (1970-1982) and Executive Committee (1946-1980) make up the Committees series.
    - Council
      The SRC Council acted on basic policy and elected members of the SRC Executive Committee.
      - Membership 1970-1974 (Box 26)
    - Executive Committee 1946-1980
      The Executive Committee was responsible for executive actions such as approving proposals, requesting use of overhead, appointing committees and receiving their reports. The minutes and agendas of this committee date from 1946 to 1982 and provide an excellent outline of issues of importance to SRC such as salary and promotion policies, the organization of SRC and its relationship to other units within ISR, and funding sources. There are gaps in the minutes for the 1960s.
      - Minutes and Agendas
        - 1970-1982, 5 folders (Box 26)
      - Minutes and Agendas
        - November 1946-December 1948 (Box 26)
        - September 1951-December 1952 (Box 26)
        - 1953-1963, 10 folders (Box 27)
        - January-May 1964, July-October 1965, September-December 1966, March-December 1969 (Box 27)
        - January 1970-June 1972 (Box 27)
        - July 1972-June 1981, 9 folders (Box 27)
        - July 1981-September 1982 (Box 28)
      - Background Materials 1972-1980, 14 folders (Box 28)
      - Index to Minutes 1970/71-1980/81, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Notes from Meetings 1950-1960 (Box 29)
    - Omnibus Survey Steering Committee
      For a more detailed look at a survey research project, the researcher could review the Omnibus Survey Steering Committee minutes (1972-1975) which document the Omnibus household survey begun in 1972. How researchers conducted a survey is reflected here, as are concerns such as reducing survey costs, research design, efforts to broaden the base of support for the survey, and logistical details.
      - Minutes, notes etc. 1972-1975, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Primary Research Staff Meeting Agendas and Minutes
      The Primary Research Staff Meeting Agendas (1983-1986, 1989-1990) give the researcher an opportunity to learn how researchers at SRC worked with each other, and one will find good discussions of the internal organization and governance of SRC, overhead issues, project proposals, salary policies, appointments, recruitment and long-range planning.
      - 1983-1986, 5 folders (Box 29)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 29)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2020 ]
    - Program Directors Meetings
      The Program Directors Meetings minutes (1975-1982) complement the Primary Research Staff meetings, as they reflect the responsibility of the group for tenure decisions, general policy issues and salary proposals. This group of records documents decisions made and discussions about types of research, computing systems, reviews and evaluations, and hiring and promotion.
      - 1975/76-1981/82, 5 folders (Box 29)
    - Senior Staff Advisory Committee Agendas and Minutes. 1984-1985, 1990s
      The Senior Staff Advisory Committee Agendas and Minutes (1984-1986, 1990) document a committee that was initiated by SRC Director Howard Schuman, in order that he might obtain advice more easily. The committee was to assist in information gathering and advance planning and to give him a sense of senior staff views. Committee members were elected. Many of the same issues addressed by the Primary Research Staff are addressed by this committee.
      - July 1984-1986, 11 folders (Box 30)
      - April-June 1990, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Senior Staff Discussions 1950-1953
      Rich documentation of SRC staff concerns and working relationships in the early years of the organization is available in the Senior Staff Discussions (1950-1953). Questions reflected in the discussions include what kinds of research SRC should be conducting, organization within the Center and the issue of programmatic research. The goals of the Center as a social science organization and its role in the international arena, discussions of proposals, its relationship to RCGD, how policy is formed in the Center and discussions of committee reports are all touched upon in these records.
      - October 1950-March 1953 (Box 31)
      - Senior Staff Meetings 1982/83 (Box 51)
      - Notes, Agendas etc. 1982/83 (Box 31)
    - Staff Meeting Agendas 1955-1961 (Box 31)
  - Director's Files 1976-1990
    The Director's Files consist of Correspondence (2 linear feet) and Topical Files (7 linear feet).
    - Correspondence 1976-1990
      Correspondence is arranged in two segments, chronological and general. The chronological correspondence dates from 1976 to 1990 and is almost exclusively between ISR staff; it concerns meetings, issues relating to hiring and interviewing, and other administrative issues relating to SRC. The general correspondence dates from 1976 to 1990 and is primarily to and from individuals outside ISR. Arranged chronologically, it is useful for information on proposed surveys and projects as documented through correspondence with funding agencies. Correspondents also include potential researchers and visitors to ISR and those requesting information on the work of SRC.
      - Chronological
        - 1976/77-1981/82, 9 folders (Box 31)
        - July 1984 to April, 1985, 3 folders (Box 31)
        - May-June 1985 (Box 32)
        - 1985/86, 2 folders (Box 32)
        - 1989/90, 3 folders (Box 32)
      - General
        - 1976/77-1982/83, 7 folders (Box 32)
        - 1984/85-1985/86, 2 folders (Box 33)
        - 1989/90 (Box 33)
    - Topical Files 1976-1990
      The Topical Files date from 1976 to 1990, with a gap from 1986 to 1989, and document the responsibilities of the SRC director in his role overseeing the research and administrative aspects of SRC as well as the interaction of SRC with other units in ISR. The files are arranged topically within each calendar year. Much of the information relates to the administrative details, especially financial, of various projects and programs. Included in the project and program files, however, are status reports and requests for additional resources which often provide an overview of specific research projects or discussions of proposed projects. One can also follow the development of various computer related projects within SRC, an integral part of the work done at ISR, by looking at the computer-related files for each year. They include documentation on the development of the Computer Aided Telephone Interviewing system and OSIRIS, an integrated system of general-purpose computer programs developed by the SRC and CPS computer support groups and designed to handle the large data sets and complex management and analysis procedures that typify much social research. The files on teaching document the courses taught each year by SRC staff and the policies files include discussions of various policies and their implementation within SRC.
      - 1976/77
        - ISR (Box 33)
          - Center for Political Studies (Box 33)
          - Center for the Research Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (Box 33)
          - General Funds and Teaching (Box 33)
          - ISR Newsletter (Box 33)
          - Research Center for Group Dynamics (Box 33)
        - SRC
          - Administration (Box 33)
          - Coding (Box 33)
          - Computer Support Group (Box 33)
          - Economic Behavior (Box 33)
          - Family and Sex Roles (Box 33)
          - Field (Box 33)
          - Group Identification and Socialization (Box 33)
          - Interview Methodology (Box 33)
          - Organizational Behavior (Box 33)
          - Organizational Psychology (Box 33)
          - Pending Proposals (Box 33)
          - Policies (Box 33)
          - Possible Sources of Funds for New Research (Box 33)
          - Project Financial Information (Box 33)
          - Publishing (Box 33)
          - Publishing Board Minutes (Box 33)
          - Sampling (Box 33)
          - Space (Box 33)
          - Survey Operations in Other Countries (Box 33)
          - Urban Environmental (Box 33)
      - 1977/78
        - Department of Psychology (Box 33)
        - Departmental Associates (Box 33)
        - International Activities at UM (Box 33)
        - ISR
          - Budget (Box 33)
          - Business Office (Box 33)
          - Building Addition (Box 33)
          - Center for Political Studies (Box 33)
          - Center for the Research Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (Box 33)
          - General Funds and Teaching (Box 33)
          - General (Box 33)
          - Library (Box 33)
        - SRC
          - Coding (Box 33)
          - Committees
            - Ad Hoc Committee on Data Processing (Box 33)
            - Committee on Privacy (Box 33)
            - Subcommittee on Problems of Confidentiality of Respondents (Box 33)
          - Computer Services Facility (Box 33)
          - Computer Support Group (Box 33)
          - Computing in SRC (Box 33)
          - Economic Behavior (Box 33)
          - Economic Outlook (Box 33)
          - Family and Sex Roles (Box 33)
          - Field (Box 33)
          - Group Identification and Socialization (Box 33)
          - Interview Methodology (Box 33)
          - Organizational Behavior (Box 33)
          - Organizational Psychology (Box 33)
          - Outside Employment (Box 33)
          - Program Directors (Box 33)
          - Psychiatry (Box 33)
          - Quality of Life Project (Box 33)
          - Reorganization (Box 33)
          - Sampling (Box 34)
          - Social Indicators (Box 34)
          - Space (Box 34)
          - Special Duty Assignments (SDAs) (Box 34)
          - Staff Involvement in Departmental Teaching (Box 34)
          - Surveys of Consumer Attitudes (Box 34)
          - Urban Environmental (Box 34)
          - Youth In Transition/Monitoring the Future (Box 34)
      - 1978/79
        - ISR
          - Center for Political Studies (Box 34)
          - Center for the Research Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (Box 34)
          - General (Box 34)
          - Budget (Box 34)
          - Business Office (Box 34)
          - Library (Box 34)
        - SRC
          - Affirmative Action (Box 34)
          - Coding (Box 34)
          - Computer Services Facility (Box 34)
          - Computer Support Group (Box 34)
          - Computing (Box 34)
          - Economic Behavior (Box 34)
          - Family and Sex Roles (Box 34)
          - Field (Box 34)
          - Group Identity and Socialization (Box 34)
          - Interview Methodology (Box 34)
          - Organizational Behavior (Box 34)
          - Organizational Psychology (Box 34)
          - Policies (Box 34)
          - Publishing (Box 34)
          - Quality of Life Project (Box 34)
          - Research Center for Group Dynamics (Box 34)
          - Sampling (Box 34)
          - Science and Society (Box 34)
          - Social Environment & Mental Health (Box 34)
          - Special Duty Assignments and Assignment to Duty Off Campus (Box 34)
          - Urban Environment (Box 34)
      - 1979/80
        - ISR
          - Budget (Box 34)
          - Business Office (Box 34)
          - Center for the Research Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK) (Box 34)
          - General Funds (Box 34)
          - Research Center for Group Dynamics Search Committee (Box 34)
        - SRC
          - Administration (Box 34)
          - Affirmative Action (Box 34)
          - Archiving Data (Box 34)
          - Assignment to Duty Off Campus (Box 34)
          - Chinatown Housing and Health Research Project (Box 34)
          - Coding (Box 34)
          - Computer Services Facility (Box 34)
          - Computer Support Group (Box 34)
          - Economic Behavior (Box 34)
          - Exchange (Box 34)
          - Family and Sex Roles (Box 34)
          - Field (Box 34)
          - Group Identity and Socialization (Box 34)
          - Human Subjects Policy (Box 34)
          - Interview Methodology (Box 34)
          - Organizational Behavior (Box 34)
          - Organizational Psychology (Box 34)
          - Outside Offers (Box 34)
          - Outside Employment (Box 34)
          - Program Directors (Box 51)
          - Proposals Pending (Box 34)
          - Publishing (Box 34)
          - Recruitment (Box 34)
          - Responses to Proposals (Box 34)
          - Sampling (Box 34)
          - Science and Society (Box 34)
          - Social Environment and Mental Health (Box 34)
          - Social Indicators (Box 34)
          - Special Duty Assignment (Box 34)
          - Space (Box 34)
          - Urban Environment (Box 34)
          - Youth in Transition/Monitoring the Future (Box 34)
        - School of Public Health (Box 34)
      - 1980/81
        - Department of Psychology (Box 51)
        - Department of Sociology (Box 34)
        - ISR
          - Business Office (Box 34)
          - Center for Political Studies (Box 51)
          - Center for the Research Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK) (Box 34)
          - General and General Funds, 2 folders (Box 34)
          - Research Center for Group Dynamics (Box 34)